Xiaoqin Feng (冯小琴)

Online version: https://xqfeng-josie.github.io/resume/cv

Last updated: November 3, 2024

Curriculum Vitae

Google Scholar 🏶

XqFeng-Josie 😱

Introduction

I am currently a Tech Lead at Mobvoi AI Lab, specializing in AI product development, research, and interactive application design. My core responsibilities encompass the entire product lifecycle, including data construction, performance evaluation, algorithm optimization, and facilitating effective product communication to align cross-functional teams. Additionally, I play a crucial role in managing team members and coordinating resources. I am committed to developing products that are driven by user needs and data insights, making me a versatile contributor to AI projects.

EDUCATION

Master Student Software Engineer (M.Sc.)

Beijing University of Technology BJUT; overall grade: 86 (max. 100) between "Very Good" and "Good"

Beijing, China

Bachelor Student Computer Science (B.Eng.)

Southwest Minzu University SMU; overall grade: 3.66 (max. 4.0), "Top 5" of 154 students

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2016

Oct. 2016 - Jan. 2019

Chengdu, China

Professional Experience

Tech Lead

[Mobvoi]

May. 2023 – Present

Beijing, China

- **Product Support**: Delivered full-time support for AI products by managing requirement communication, coordinating cross-functional teams, and ensuring timely program delivery
- **Performance Evaluation**: Conducted comprehensive performance evaluations of algorithms and products to drive continuous optimization and ensure product quality
- Data Pipeline Development: Designed and maintained robust multimodal data collection pipelines, enabling data-driven decision-making and supporting key product development initiatives

Senior Speech algorithm Engineer

Jul. 2019 - May. 2023

[Mobvoi]

Beijing, China

- Researcher: Expertise in TTS and NLP technologies, including tokenization, text normalization, polyphone disambiguation, prosody modeling,
 emotion detection, and unified-model development
- · Developer: Developed and maintained TTS and NLP-based systems to support product deployment and scalability
- Product Support: Participated in the incubation and design of AI algorithm products
- Mentor: working with 3 interns (annual) in NLP and Text-to-speech(TTS)

Algorithm Research(Intern)

Aug. 2018 - Dec. 2018

Sep. 2016 - Aug. 2018

TAL AI Lab

Others

Beijing, China

- Researcher: Developed a Deep Knowledge Tracing (DKT) pipeline to evaluate various methods, including data mining, weight graph construction, graph embedding, and metric distance analysis
- **Key results**: Outstanding Intern of 10 members; one co-author submission to *AIED2019*; (*)regular staff opportunity

IOT-Lab

Beijing, China

- - DeeCamp AI Lab: Movie Recommendation based on knowledge graph(KG) (co- with two Ph.D. three M.Sc.)
- · Ali Tianchi Competition CCF: User Location Prediction, O2O coupon usage predictions e.g.
- · TAL AI Lab: FutrueCamp: Research on Recommendation Systems, after that I got an internship
- - TextCNN: Methods are implemented based on TF-IDF, xgboost, lgb, textcnn, etc. code
- · Dialogue Generation: Simmc2 task: Methods are implemented based on BERT, GPT, Multimodal, etc.
- · IoT Bus HD Intelligent Video Surveillance: Programming and development of application algorithms
- - IOT-AI Video Analyser: Programming and development of application algorithms

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

Ali Tianchi Competition Sep. 2018

Good, 19/2845

Beijing, China

National Scholarship Sep. 2016

Southwest Minzu University

Chengdu, China

Outstanding Secretary of the Youth League Scholarship

Chengdu, China

Southwest Minzu University

Sep. 2013

May 2014

Annual Excellent Student Innovative Project

Chengdu, China

Southwest Minzu University, 2nd Award

Outstanding Student Scholarship

Jun. 2013,Jun. 2014

Southwest Minzu University

Chengdu, China

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lecture - Embedded System Design Practice

2018Winter

As teaching assistant at BJUT, for M.Sc. students, approx. 80 students each year.

Company - Speech & NLP

2021-present

Annual

As a mentor at Mobvoi, for interns (students), annual. 3 students.

Publications

Proceedings

- Feng X, Xie R, Sheng J, et al. *Population statistics algorithm based on MobileNet.* Journal of Physics: Conference Series. IOP Publishing, 2019, 6 pages. ICSP'2019.
- Wang Z, Feng X, Tang J, et al. *Deep Knowledge Tracing with Side Information*. International conference on artificial intelligence in education. Springer, Cham, 2019, 5 pages. AIED'2019.
- Rong Xie, Feng X A method of quick edge detection based on Zynq. International Conference on Cloud Computing and Internet of Things, 2018, 5
 pages. CCIOT'2018
- Sheng J, Feng X Research on the Internet of Things Platform for Smart and Environmental Protection. International Conference on Cloud Computing and Intelligence Systems, 2018, 5 pages. CCIS'2018
- Chi W, Feng X(*euqal contribution), Chen Y, et al. 2M-NER: Contrastive Learning for Multilingual and Multimodal NER with Language and Modal Fusion. Applied Intelligence, 2024, 5 pages.APASIPA'23
- Wang D, Feng X, Liu Z, et al. 2M-NER: contrastive learning for multilingual and multimodal NER with language and modal fusion[J]. Applied Intelligence, 2024: 1-17. 5 pages Applied Intelligence'2024

Patents

- FENG XIAOQIN, et al.. Polyphone labeling method and device, and computer readable storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2019,CN111078898A
- FENG XIAOQIN et al. Speech synthesis method and device and computer readable storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2020,CN110970013A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Polyphone labeling method and device, and computer readable storage medium.

 Mobvoi(application),2020,CN111145724A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Construction method and device of rhythm model, rhythm labeling method and electronic equipment.
 Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115470351A

- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Construction method and device of rhythm model, rhythm labeling method and electronic equipment. Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115470350A
- FENG XIAOQIN, et al. Voice synthesis method and device, electronic equipment and storage medium. Mobvoi(algorithm),2022,CN115547289A
- other 4 co-patents: CN111079428A CN111178042A CN115578998A CN116013251A

Theses

- Xiaoqin Feng. 2019. Research on multi-scene video intelligent processing system and scheduling management algorithm. In the Institute of Software Engineering. Beijing University of Technology. 78 pages. Master Thesis. https://kns.cnki.net/master_thesis.pdf
- Xiaoqin Feng. 2016. *Intelligent Laboratory Management System*. In the Institute of Computer Science and Engineering. Southwest Minzu University. 37 pages. **Bachelor Thesis**.